[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings to relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio was brought to you by I Triple
E software magazine online at computer
or / software house of engineering grade
yo this is about both I'm sitting here
with fro-ing huh totally and welcome to
the show
florian is the CEO of a scare huh your
concerns he here in Germany he is
co-founder of Russ Berlin and he is also
part of the global Roskam unity group
he has written quite a number of
articles and blog post about rust so
obviously our main subject today will be
the rust language first off why did
Mozilla even start Russ what niche does
it fill first of all Mozilla didn't
start Russ directly it was the Hobby
project of a Muslim research employee
green hua which was later adopted by
Mozilla rich research themselves the
niche it fills is a replacement for the
system's programming languages that
muslin tree uses Mosul as a heavy user
of C and C++ and rust is an attempt to
make these programming environments
safer so for a lot of parts they're
currently using it for the browser
development but also for all the other
native targets concerning systems
programming there are quite a few other
languages that are also becoming popular
in the last few years
for example goes so what's the
difference to those other new popular
languages so the main difference to go
is that deluge has a runtime that is
necessary to run go programs
rust doesn't have one in the classical
sense so there is no garbage collector
in the language there's no runtime
library that you need to link and where
would you use rust obviously Mozilla has
projects that that are using it but why
would I use it over other languages I
would use it anywhere we're currently C
is still popular for me who's originally
from
from the Ruby world rust fills the niche
of being another language that you can
drop down to one your scripting language
becomes too slow
rust can be used to implement an émigré
libraries that you can later use to the
FFI of your language so these are
classical places or just for standalone
web server or CLI tools we already
talked about how Russ started off as a
hobby project can you say a few more
words about the history and where it
comes from the history is pretty long
one so to say rust was first announced
in or first publicly released in 2010
and committed to github and back then
the language looked much different from
how it looked like today which was also
the reason why I joined it around three
years ago because it was definitely a
programming language in the making and
you don't have that very often that you
can look at how the they evolved and at
the beginning rust was a language that
was fully focused on concurrent
programming did ship with the runtime
did ship with primitives for concurrent
programming and I think because go was
at the same time becoming popular that
shifted a lot because go was already a
concurrent programming language with the
runtime so Russ moved away towards we
want to bring all these kind of stuff to
lower parts of the stack how did the
evolution of Russ actually take place I
mean usually there is like a language
specification then you implement the
specification and then you extend later
on is that also what Russ did or did
they use a different approach they used
to be a write down a line of
specification at some point and there
was an implementation of the compiler
first no camel later replaced by a
compiler in written in rust which was
then constantly evolved on Vario
early on there was a release process
introduced which was later changed but
all Mozilla projects need to have a
release process and an RFC process so
even before the language was finished
all changes needed to be proposed all
larger changes need to do you need to be
proposed and we still have a track
record of all the larger changes while
they were implemented or why features
were cut before really stuff actually
features removed from the language or
was it just extended there were a lot of
features we move in the beginning I just
mentioned that Russ doesn't have a
garbage collector when it was first
released publicly it had a garbage
collector which was optional in which
were then later removed one interesting
thing about the whole evolution is that
there was always a large project that
was developed in lockstep with rust
which is several maybe touch on that
later so a lot of theories about how the
language could work where we were
actually able to test on a large project
for example the removal of the garbage
collector was we tried to implement
several without GC and when we figured
out that this works we don't need this
we had the GC as some kind of okay we're
not sure if our system holds so we can
always grab into the candy box and use
garbage collection and that was removed
after we managed to find out that we can
implement server without so probably the
language can live without interesting
because I mean usually I think languages
are just extended and you know glue
features over time and removing stuff as
phenomena so garbage collectors quite
unusual I think what's the syntax like I
mean nowadays it seems there's either
either the language to see like or Ruby
like so what about rust it's a little
mix so it's it's see like in the sense
that we have curly braces and everything
it has genetics that look like C++ Java
the syntax with anchor brackets and it
is an expression based syntax like Ruby
so you don't need explicit returns
everything like the last statement of an
evaluation is also the return of that
evaluation so it's done like a natural
parent language that rust evolved from
or that it was based on not quite it is
the first productive implementation of
the kind of tied system rust uses that I
know of so there's definitely some
research work that predates it it has
influence
from a lot of other languages a lot of
the engineers that work on it have a C
and C++ background so there's definitely
some some of that and it also shows that
if you see newcomers to the language you
can with some experience tell which
language they come from kind of shows
that it's a mix of many styles that
people can then also reuse so talking
about about research it seems that Russ
is more like a language that was grown
from the practical side of things or
does it have like a strong academic
background too
it's an interesting mix it's written at
Mozilla research but with the definite
goal of going to what practical use
especially after it was decided that the
line should actually be released as a
100 it started to become far and far
more practical and it has a lot of
convenience features that show that
everyone working on the language had
ample experience with other programming
environments let's talk about the
features and what the language actually
feels like so first of all is Russ type
safe yes
versus type safe safe rest will never
SEC fault it also on top of that gives
safety guarantees to concurrent programs
and uses the type information for a lot
of compiler optimizations so yes the
type system is at the core and it's
important is the language statically
typed on dynamically typed it statically
types and it does a lot a lot of checks
doing static at the static point of
compilation it does have almost no
dynamic features at runtime that you
don't have to opt into maybe explaining
that later but the Russ compiler catches
most errors it catches at compile time
you said that you are from a ruby
eccrine and obviously Ruby's
dynamically it's hot so don't you feel
like that you're limited in your and
your freedom and your flexibility if you
switch over to statically typed language
not quite it has certain trade-offs
sometimes you have to work for
things more than you've feel like you'd
have to in your favorite dynamic
language on the other hand it get also
gives a lot of guarantees I know at
every point what type I'm using I know
at every point what's going to happen if
I do this and this function call it has
a very predictable performance
characteristics and especially when it
comes to concurrent programming rust
gives you a lot of help in catching
unsafe patterns there so it's rust
object-oriented no it may look like it
sometimes so you can define functions on
top of structures that do take a self
parameter which looks a lot like Python
but this is more of a syntactic
convenience at a lot of places it
doesn't have methods in the sense that I
can send messages it has no message
passing at all so all the
object-oriented features beyond having
methods are completely missing also
inheritance
I assume inheritance is missing at least
structural inheritance is missing we're
going to cover traits later traits can
depend on others which is a form of
inheritance but you cannot describe data
structures in the sense of this is the
same but with a few additional fields
but you can have such as it seems but
then you would have functions separated
from those structures in a different yet
functions and state are always separated
we already sort of spoke about it so
what are structures or structs structs
are if you come from C C++ world
basically what you know is structs it's
the description of a data structure and
it's memory layout so the memory layout
of data structures and rust is currently
not defined my change of compiler
versions can force the compiler to lay
it out like C would lay them out but
there's not much more to beyond that why
would I do that I would have thought
that you know accessing the struct and
relying on how it's in the memory is
sort of peckish the layering like C part
is just there for being able to pass the
structure over to a C program and back
so
that's an FFA feature other than that
for for example compiled optimization
reasons and fields may be reordered this
is really just for this certain place
where I want that also well for example
if I interface both my operating system
they still got capr as they expect
something to be in a in a specific
layout so we can provide
that's a heavy use case of rust I see
yeah to to interface with see that makes
a lot of sense so what about traits
traits are implemented on top of
structures so I can have a I can have a
trait that defines a certain set of
methods that take the structure and I
implement it on as for example the soft
parameter and do certain things with it
we also call these functions methods
because they do have a soft parameter as
first parameter but they are independent
of the data structure I later create the
mapping of this data structure
implements this trade this trade this
trade and they generally use in the
sense of I have an equal trade equal
means that all data structures of that
type it can be compared or I have other
traits that mark the structure for this
is safe for sharing this is unsafe for
sharing and all these kind of things how
does that actually work what I say okay
this is the struck that implements that
equal train is that how it works yes
okay but when I have an equal trade
actually I only say that there should be
a method somewhere that allows me to
compare two structs it doesn't say
anything about the data structure does
it exactly so they're independent of the
internal structure oh I see so it's rate
wouldn't say that this data is part of
the struct it will just say that there
are some methods that you could use on
it exactly so in the case of the equal
trade I would need to implement like an
equal method for all of the of the types
or all of the strikes that would
implement that trade
exactly then they're armed algebraic
data types what about those how does
that work
algebraic data types or unifications of
other type for example the classic is
the option type
which we also nowadays in Java and Scala
or in others which has two forms it's
either I have some data or I have none
which avoids having to have a null
pointer in the language so no data is
basically a value in the sense of
programming and especially on all
interfaces I see that this is optional
or not
compared to Java for example where
basically any parameter can be null and
I have to check for that all the time in
rust I can express this is optional this
is not and this end you need to check
for it if it's optional we need you need
to unwrap that option at some point and
find out what's inside or if there's
nothing and would that be implemented is
struct or is it a separate concept we
call them enums so there's the enum
keyword which introduces all variants of
that enum so the option enum would
basically be it's optional for some
struct and then it has some tea
or unknown as the two variants there is
another another important one of those
types which is the result type which is
used all through a trusts which has the
two variants there's a result or there
is an arrow for any kind of operation
and the other nice thing is because
there are types you can implement
methods on them so options and results
can be combined so there are no
exceptions obviously but that is
something that you would do with the
results in general rest there are no
exceptions yes they we do have some form
of exceptions which is called panicking
so there's always the case that a
program goes completely amiss in that
case we panic and that's implementation
what is equivalent to a c++ exception so
stack gets enrolled and everything but
that's not for a normal program flow and
cannot be recovered so you already said
that an option would be an option of T
so it seems there is parametric
polymorphism and generics in place stat
how it works
we do have generics I also thought that
at the beginning that we have a generic
syntax that's similar to Java so structs
and functions can be generic over the
arguments and option is an example so
you have option T which is always a sum
of that type or no another interesting
fact about the optional type by the way
is that it's data layout is similar to
having a null pointer or not so you can
pass it again
to see just normal as as you would
usually use it what about macros what
are they rust has hygienic macros rust
can be a rather Weber's language so
macro use is very very common especially
for patterns where you have a number of
structs with a very very standard
implementation of a certain trait people
often write a macro for providing that
implementation was just the fill ends of
the struct name and all these kind of
things for example when it comes to
equals and all these kind of things
people just don't want to implement
equals for each type and then all its
sub fields and everything like that so
their macros are used very often there's
also a number of libraries that provide
for example passo combinators which use
macros for getting a cleaner interface
there depending on if you like macros
what what kind of operators would be
implemented they would for example
implement combinators for passes using a
macro so for example I have a parser
that pauses as a string how do those
macros work is it like like in C where
it's just texts that get expanded or is
it somehow a higher level programming
feature basis of language basically for
us for any kind of macro they take
certain set of tokens and you need to
provide the macro with a description of
what these are are they keywords are
they feels then this macro gets the
exponent at that point as I said the
hygienic macros so they're not just text
replacements the compiler will add
expansion time check
whether the code coming out of that
makes sense and point towards errors in
the macro expansion that can be a little
verbose because micros might expand
macros and all that but the compiler can
actually detect errors within the macro
definition that you're hitting and not
in the sense that you need to find out
what happened and then deduce from the
final source code so would you call them
idiomatic is that something that you
would use smoke holes macros are
idiomatic definitely for example just
the standard print line in rust as a
macro because standard by foot
implementation of printing to standard
out would be getting a handle to
standard out locking standard out
writing to standard out interpolating a
string that you write to standard out
and we got that all wrapped into a macro
so there'd definitely idiomatic there's
also another commonly used macro which
is called try which takes all of these
results and if it is an error
immediately returns out of the function
that is called in and otherwise gives
you the value back so it returns breaks
early and returns the error out of a
function or gives you the value back and
that's very very common one that you
couldn't live without so the two
examples that you gave far more like
seemed to me more like parts of the
language course or to say or let's say
the the standard libraries but you write
and make for yourself as a feature that
you would use as normal developer or
just for library developers yes there's
definitely micro sets as libraries which
are important and interesting and as I
said rust can become rather the boughs
but at some point so providing macros
for standard patterns is definitely
idiomatic before we we started the
interviews you said that actually you
you thought that there were some issues
with my clothes so can you explain that
I have personal issues with macros I
think macros point a little towards
flaws in the language for example
extreme velocity around some features
and are fixed that I don't like that
much but that
tends to come from the point that I'm
from the Ruby world what a lot of these
things can be expressed in the Ruby
language itself I don't see any need for
micros in Ruby because well it usually
has that boot face for all applications
we can change the whole runtime system
which we don't have and rust so it's
probably the fix for that
what about functions what are functions
in rust functions in rest are either
just normal functions as no them so we
have bare functions that just take
parameters and return functions can't be
generic so you can say well I have a
function that does something on anything
that's comparable or all these kind of
things functions the same as all the
others before can be forced to follow
the C API of the platform so you can use
them as callbacks to C libraries and all
these kinds of things the function is a
pretty much standard I can also have
them on a trait for example with the
implicit self parameter we do have
closures in the language too as a
separate concept and functions and
closures are separate especially because
functions don't close I can't have inner
function definitions within a function
but functions don't close there's a
strict separation with that language can
you elaborate on the difference between
a closure and a function a closure has
access to the environment around the
definition of the closure so it can
access variables that were outside of
the closure if you have an inner
function that you define for example for
a callback or something like that you
cannot do that so you would either have
access to sort of the outside world or
not and rust supports both that's what
you said right yeah Russ support both
what about higher-order functions and
all these advanced function programming
paradigms a bit tricky currently it's
usually not used what we do have in the
sense of functional programming is that
our iterative API uses the map filter
and produced paradigm but I wouldn't
call that
functional programming in the sense that
you return functions that are prevalent
to parameters and all these kind of
things but at least you can pass in
functions as parameters to a map
function that would then execute the
function on each a member of an array or
something like that but no not really
the advanced features that you would
find in a true function programming
language yes okay at the very beginning
you said that Russ was actually quite
useful for concurrent programming yes so
what is Russ approach towards mutability
I mean obviously if you talk about
concurrency it's very easy as long as
you don't have mutable state so you know
those are two related issues I would say
Russ approach to mutability is rather
direct there's this classical problem in
concurrent programming that shared
mutable state is problematic but if you
have a close look at the statement the
problem is that sharing and mutability
at the same time is problematic so what
Russ does it takes these concepts by
themselves and says ok so first let's
approach mutability and make it a first
class concept of language so every
variable binding that you introduce is
either mutable or not mutable by the
keyword muta and if it's not mutable you
cannot use it you cannot change it in
any way and every time you pass access
to some of your values to another part
of the programming program you also have
to mark whether it's in a mutable
fashion or not so it's kind of on the
question of whether we're a programming
language that models immutable data or
mutable data we're both in the sense but
it's a first class concept and the
compiler will deduce different things
based on the mutability of you values I
would actually use the keyword to mark
it as immutable variable right and then
the type checker would catch issues if I
have you know mutable stuff or immutable
stuff that gets passed to something that
should be mutable
so it's it's an extension of the type
system it's part of the type system so
at a lot of places the Moodle for
exemption is a type I'm getting a bit
ahead of you here but sharing is a type
in rust and the mutable fashion and the
immutable fashion are both different
types that follow different rules and
that's a very important part there about
for the safety guarantees that we're
going to talk about later but also in
the non-shared data case that's already
pretty interesting because there's a
very good blog post but one of the
server engineers that says if you have a
sufficiently large single threaded
program you're already running into
problems that are similar to concurrent
programming for example I pass a value
into a huge library and I cannot safely
figure out whether that library will
mutate it or not and in rust you can
safely do that because the interface
says okay you get it an immutable
fashion or not and I can then assume
that you have mutated or need to assume
that you might have mutated it okay so
actually gives me more guarantees about
the code and therefore it makes it
easier to figure out what the code
actually does it's a very explicit
that's the advantage of rust velocity
it's very explicit at all places and
especially around meat ability it's
always clear if you can change something
or not I think we will put a link to the
blog post in the show notes so you can
look it up later on ok excellent that's
the part about how to have separate
mutability and immutable data there's
also a concept of ownership so can you
talk about that
so every time you introduce about you
into a program Russ allocated somewhere
I don't stack on the heap you're the
owner of of it and they can only ever be
one owner of every piece of data that's
fundamental to how rust works that's
statically guaranteed and that also
means that we can statically ensure that
we find out when you're not going to use
that value anymore and then remove it
from memory and drop it the ownership
while the simple rules you either have
it and then you can do everything with
that value or you can pass it on for
example in the sense of when we're
talking about mobility um if you own the
value you can even decide okay this is
mutable but I'm just gonna make it
mutable because there's no other party
involved the static guarantee is you
have ownership you can do whatever you
like with it and once it drops out of
scope it will be removed or you
explicitly call a function that removes
it yeah I found that interesting so you
said once there is no owner of some data
it would get removed that sounds a lot
like garbage collection but before you
said that there was actually no garbage
collector in rust yes that's a
statically proven at compile time where
the value needs to be removed so this we
get a little bit into terminology
problems there with whoever we talk to
like a lot of people that come from the
Java world are pretty much fine with if
you say okay the compiler will introduce
that call during compile time and
they're like okay that's no garbage
collection others and any time they
don't have to call free by themselves
they're more like okay but this is
garbage collection in some fashion the
problem there being that the term
garbage collection not being very well
defined so that you can already see that
in Python Python has reference coding
and some people call that carpet
collection of those insists that it's
reference counting and not in the sense
of a garbage collector and for us that
is all happening at compile time with
opt in towards one time Hertz so if you
need more because you can only have one
handle on any kind of data this is
sometimes impractical we have special
kind of pointer which is part of the
language standard library but not in any
way special in rust that is for example
a ref counted pointer which allows you
to have multiple handles on it and any
time people drop these handles counters
count it down but that's opt in at all
times but how does that fit to the owner
ship paradigm so because because in a
way what you're saying is in that case
there is there are multiple parts of the
code that would have a pointer to that
piece of data and once all those are
gone then it would get removed from
memory the way it works in that sense is
a pass away ownership to the RC type
then I own the RC and can get handles of
that which I want again so the whole
system runs pretty deep I can always say
ok I own something and I wrap it into
another thing that I own which gives
additional possibilities to work with it
so what's our C RC would be ref counter
okay I see so so basically I'm taking
that piece of data I pass it on to the
ref counting and then I can pass on
those references to other parts of the
code and they would own that but I would
still own the original data
what about boring boring is the
companion to ownership because I always
passing on ownership can be problematic
I need to give ownership to all parts of
the program they need to give it back
and usually what you do in most C style
language is you just pass on the
reference to other parts of the program
and this process in rust is called
borrowing for the reason that there's
additional rules involved behind the
concept is basically just passing
references somewhere else with borrowing
it's again the same I can either borrow
immutably or I can borrow immutably
which allows the other party to do
whatever they want what but I was
allowed with it and as I mentioned
before the Moodle borrow and the
standard borrow are different things so
for example if I have a crate that
implements functions on mutable borrows
and some on immutable borrows it might
be that I cannot call all everywhere
depending on how the piece of data I
have was shared with me so it allows for
certain operations to be done or not and
the important rule in borrowing is I can
share something immutably through borrow
as often as I'd like or I can share it
muta bleah
once but never both of it so it's never
allowed that immutable burrow and an
immutable burrow is active at the same
time and that's statically proven again
and the problem obviously being the the
concurrency problem if I have an
immutable burrow I want to be sure that
it's actually move immutable if I read
it twice it must be the same value and
that cannot be guaranteed if someone
else has a mutable or own active right
what about scent and shrink that's
another concept for concurrency so then
sand and sink are markers that the
compiled of deduces or that you can
implement yourself if you are absolutely
sure that you build something that is
one of these things send is I can send a
value between concurrent parts of the
program like a can pass ownership
between like a thread and another thread
which means it's not available anymore
in one of those but available in the
others and sync is there's some
synchronization primitive provided
around the value which makes mutable
sharing safe so rust for example will
tell you so I have one example where I
implement a small very simple server
which is single threaded and writes to a
hash map and at some point you can start
making it multi-threaded and you start
introducing threads and suddenly the
compiler comes along and says ok now you
kind of concurrently write to that hash
map with that additional work because a
hash map by standard is not sync and
then you can again wrap it for example
in the mutex a music for example
provides sync for all the internal parts
so these are just markers that the
language provides but for example the
Mirek stats implemented on top of it
it's not a language features the library
feature there is also safety so what
does the term safety mean in the rust
world so safety means memory safety so
safe Russ programs will not produce any
illegal memory accesses
like fault there's a couple of little
confusing things around that for example
memory leaks are safe they're not only
legal memory access so the safety
guarantee here is really we don't crash
in that sense and we don't provide any
legal I'm a wrapper operations and yeah
no double freeze also and have to say in
the case that a program has to unwind
because it's been panicking at some
point there's been an out of memory
access or something we also make sure
that all values along the stack are
properly removed how would you call
unsafe C code for example there's an
unsafe some language which is introduced
by the key word unsafe if you use it you
can say unsafe or block and do unsafe
operations within it for example then
you can do pointer calculations and all
these kind of things getting producing
raw pointers using raw pointers and all
that so there most bets are off it's
still safer than in a lot of other
languages there's still compiler checks
going on for example if two things that
you are using are the same memory size
so we still have checks there but yeah
and this is for example used for calling
in to see but there's also some points
of the rest language where unsafe is
used to provide implementations for
things that are more efficient than what
you could write in safe rust this is
pretty rare it's usually around a data
structure primitives where there's known
patterns to very quickly implement them
using raw pointers yeah what I'm
wondering about is this seems to be a
rather different approach from many
other languages so are you aware of any
other languages that do similar things
or is really rough specific this
concurrency model but the concurrency
model itself is what it was successive
specific especially the approach of
having just these kind of market rates
these kinds rules around mutability
engineering and not actually
implementing something in language so
for example go has channels they're part
of the language we don't have channels
as part of the language we have tracking
from the compiler whether the things are
safe and you can implement the
abstractions on top of it yourself for
example this currently a large project
going on called Tokyo which provides an
event reactor for us programs and is
using a lot of these primitives but is
completely implemented outside of the
res compiler or outside of the standard
lab what's the result of that I mean if
you have a seeded program you can be
pretty sure that there is there might be
some buffer overflows and stuff like
that and even in a Java program you
might have memory leaks and you know in
particular the the threading model is
rather complicated so what's the result
our loss programs in your experience
very stable and very safe or others
field issues they usually rather stable
also on the on the memory leak side I
think the fact that in rust you have to
work for getting shared access to values
also make sure that you don't
accidentally get it we also catch a
couple of other bugs on so in general
yes worse programs are memory safe and I
rarely see memory leaks crashes are very
rare on standard programming use we also
catch a number of additional bugs that
are pretty often seen in other languages
for example the the nice thing about the
ownership model that we have is that it
does provide iterator invalidation for
example because suddenly if you if you
get hold of an iterator of a collection
we have additional info because we know
which part of the program we'll just
pass it on we know which one is going to
mutate it and we know which one is going
to you own it for example we can have
pass it on twice accidentally if you're
talking about the problem that if I have
an iterator of a data structure then
concurrent system might change that and
the might aerator becomes embedded
itself what you what you're talking
about
that is obviously soft in rust yes you
can never get one of the things there is
that you need access to the data
structure in a mutable fashion and
access to an iterator at the same time
which is usually prohibited by most rust
api's is the language itself extensible
in what way I mean we already spoke
about Marcos that sounds like something
that you can basically use to sort of
extend the language are the other
features there is a nightly feature
called as a rust has a nightly compiler
and a stable compiler and the nightly
compiler has certain features that this
table doesn't have there's a nightly
feature with which is compiler plugins
where you can implement other things on
top of the language get access to ast
and all these kind of things but this is
slowly moving under my impression
towards give providing extension points
so what we currently have for example is
custom ways of deriving searching for
certain features on structure is easier
so that you can't for example just say
derive jason decodable on top of a
struct and then you can decode it from
jason but this is something you don't
really want to have as a language
feature because that would fix you on
one implementation of this so this is
something we're currently working on
providing and that's landing soon as far
as I understood compiler plugins will at
some point be available as a standard
rest feature is from Pyatt or is it an
interpreter or is some using some some
kind of virtual machine it's completely
compiled all of what I've described is
completely working at compile time all
the safety guarantees are happening at
compile time the only thing that we have
as a runtime system is the
implementation of stack unwinding so I
actually get a binary that would be
directly executed just as I would in in
C or C++ yes okay I see and what's the
true chain so would I just use the
compiler or what I need to use some kind
of
bill tool in addition we ship package
manager let's call cargo implemented by
the people that implemented bumbler
before so it's not the first attempt and
so we we did a community survey I would
use that to get the libraries right you
would use that to get the libraries and
also to compile your program is if it
comes with was a set of sub commands so
you get a configuration file we give in
all the dependencies all the development
dependencies and then you get a set of
sub commands build run tests so I would
use cargo and rust the rust compile and
I'm done yes and the rest compiler
itself ships was some support for
testing so which can be driven through
cargo tests so if you after you run
cargo in it you're completely set up for
test-driven development in rust how
would I compile my how would I make sure
that my application actually works let's
here in Windows when I'm on on a Mac and
compiling it on a Mac so you can cross
compile cross compiling to Windows is
probably a little bit of a problem
because for cross compiling you need the
base libraries so there's some setup
involved but we do ship the standard
library and the core libraries
implemented for all for all important
targets including iOS Android Mac
different flavors of Linux and certain
embedded targets
Windows is a first-class target for rust
so are you sharing the compiler bacon
with I don't know the new tools or
anything like that or is it you know
custom built it's LLVM in the back hello
okay so what's not on this low-level
virtual machine currently implemented by
apple mostly which is also behind the
xcode tool chain ceiling and everything
and it's basically a compiler toolkit
and comes with well compilation support
for multiple targets so in general the
target support in rust is roughly where
Apple and Google are big ad support is
currently good if not we need to make
sure that we provide you said LLVM is
like
machine but that doesn't say that it's
actually generating bytecode that would
be interpreted at runtime no it's a
compiler tool it's it still has vm and
the name doesn't really resemble a vm in
the end it's just the name of the
project it still has the vm in it just
to confuse people can you give an
overview about the standard library and
what its well what it offers first of
all is a core and the standard library
of the language the core library is what
is needed to run all kinds of Russ
programs in the sense of you need to
have an iterative implementation because
there is a syntax for it but so you need
to provide that and then there's the
standard library on top of it
what do you mean the language forces you
to have specific parts in your library
there's a whole library that defines a
certain set of types that must be there
for the compilers a compiler Russ
program even without any kind of
libraries for example send and soon car
so core to the language they are defined
there it's a library though so if you
have any need to replace it you could
implement your own and pass it to the
compiler and it will first compile the
core library it sounds to me like it's
sort of feels like a language feature
but in fact it's not it's implemented in
the library yeah so we have a core under
standard library the core comes also was
a few additional convenience and the
option and result types for example all
these kinds of very very basic important
types are in there the standard library
itself implements your standard fare or
file access some collections it doesn't
implement a collection API in that sense
so there is no generic collection API
because of an interesting particularity
of the rest language that's not easy to
provide currently the the problem is
that we also need to track if you have
an access into a collection we need to
track on how long that collection is
alive whether that has vanished so this
makes a standard collection API like
Java map or something much much harder
than they have so just be aware that
standard collections is
set of standard implementations of
collections but it's not like you can
replace one against the other simply by
just hiding it behind a trait and just
working on top of it so I'm not sure
whether I understand what you're saying
so there are you know maps in place
right yeah but this standard library
would provide a hash map or a tree map
or something but you would have to I'm
using a hash map here I'm using a tree
map here and not import some larger
interface that says use standard map and
use one of the one of these at that
point so you it's very much bound to the
concrete implementations there but I
mean if you if you look at the map you
know all the maps provide getting
getting data from a specific key and
sending data to a specific key so it
seems like you could you know abstract a
type and I thought that is what what
traits are for but that doesn't work he
would work there has been an
implementation of that before was one
zero it was cut because it wasn't seen
it wasn't deemed very convenient and
very hard to extend and so what was
decided that it's currently not being
implemented until we have found better
ways to implement that it's also a
problem of a language sometimes you
don't fully understand the patterns that
might emerge from a programming language
you define at some point or maybe
features a missing for all these kind of
things so it was opted for we shipping
the data structures in a proper
implementation but not the glue on top
of it in reaction that I actually do
want to change the implementation of a
map that I'm using what would happen I
mean obviously I would need to say okay
I'm using let's say a tree map instead
of hash map that's the example that you
gave and then what's left to do you
would probably at some point change a
lot of the accesses to them - the map -
because actually the the methods would
be called differently no the message
will be called the same some might
behave differently and there's
additional methods for example on the
hash map to get hold of an entry of the
hash map in a different fashion as for
tree map so there's a lot of specialized
methods on top of that
which you probably would like to use so
this is more where it this is diverging
they all have gotten set is that an
issue in real life or is it just sort of
only damages the aesthetics of the
language I haven't found a lot of people
that mentioned that as a real issue
because many many programs that we have
probably fall into the class of okay I'm
providing some kind of functionality
like lookup for something and I'm using
a hash map in the back and I'm hiding
that behind another data type altogether
so changing that is it's an an amount of
work I can guess in about one or two
hours I have replaced that there's a lot
of complaints about the collection API
that's basically just that you cannot
control memory allocation currently so
if you want to control memory allocation
you would need to use your own
implementation level for one of these
these primitives it's a work in progress
in that part it's just not that anyone
would complain that what's there is bad
so that was the thing we wanted to
ensure that the things that we have are
usable and usable in the general use
case for example the complaint about the
hash map for all of people is that that
the hash map that we use is DDoS safe so
it uses a hash function that is there's
zero safe which might not be the fastest
one and some people want fast ones but
no one's complaining about the current
implementation being bad or the input
the interface being bad so that comes a
little bit from the youngness of the
language I wouldn't say immaturity
because the implementations are mature
it's sometimes a little hit and miss so
an implementation is there or it's not
there
if it's there it's good that's what we
want to ensure and that's also the
reason why general connect collection
traits where after quite some
discussions cut before we released
language I think that makes a lot of
sense I mean looking at what person
practice is probably like the most
important thing okay so we spoke about
the the current the standard library
obviously you know every language has
quite a lot of libraries are there any
highlights
among the rust libraries I really like
the current implementation of
serialization and deserialization which
is called Surrey it's a general
serialization and deserialization
framework that you can use I'm a huge
fan of it because it's rather convenient
to use there's a couple of web
frameworks one of them is called iron
it's becoming pretty popular that I
efficient and working well and I think
the current highlights are really Tokyo
and future's so they're implemented in
lockstep futures is the futures
implementation on for rust it's just the
interface for what a future concurrency
primitive is which can be combined as as
you as you know you the futures as
concurrent operations for future
operations can be combined forked and
all these kind of things and it's pretty
interesting to look at how that looks
like in a language that has for example
no exceptions that uses results and
errors as primitives everywhere and all
these kinds of things and Tokyo is a
library where you can run these futures
on because futures are really just this
out will interface that you can
implement later that brings a little bit
of confusion a lot of people think it
comes with something but you actually if
you implement the future you need to get
something to run it on and the reason
why I find it interesting is because
there used to be a time where these be
these have been language features and it
was decided to not have them as language
features and now a lot of the people
that have been implementing these
language features two or three years ago
are now implementing them as libraries
so it's an interesting piece to look at
for those that are from the java scala
world is that Tokyo is heavily inspired
by finagle so it's basically finical
Club obviously you are working with with
rust so what are like typical
applications that you yourself do with
rust oh so I'm currently working on a
gdb client
that's more or less experimenting for me
because I'm I'm heavily interested in
cash to be and I would really like to
have a more low-level library to catch
TB than what's currently available and
all the programming languages it's
called lazy RS and for my day to day use
I implement a lot of command-line
programs on it there's also a great
command-line parser in rust which is
called clap it's highly recommendable so
there's a couple of projects that where
people basically write the third or
fourth implementation of something they
like doing and then coming over to rust
and you see really see the quality of
people that know what they're doing
doing things for the second or third
time around what are other people doing
with rust what are some popular projects
that are actually based on rust and
using rust so obviously there's the two
most of the projects they serve on
Firefox so the relationship is that
Firefox is slowly starting to adopt
features from servo which was new or is
a new implementation of a browser
rendering engine by Mozilla which is
heavily using the concurrency guarantees
that rust gives there's something that's
sometimes missed I forgot to say that
before then the nice thing about the
mutability tracking and rust is also
that it ensures that at any point were
you using a value you know if you have
if you need lock free access or not so
for a lot of places you can deduce you
can actually get away without locks
which is a much stronger thing for
concurrency and I know that Firefox for
example has problems of a kind of we are
locking something because we think they
might be concurrent access but there's
not and this tracking makes sense but
Firefox is currently mostly using URL
and media parsing libraries written in
rust because those are also the
libraries that are very they easy to run
into memory safety problems like the
string being too long feel being rate
too long like
a lot of these formers communicate okay
this things about memory layout which
brings you back to the other issue I
think we sort of covered it already so
there is an interface FFI for fun
function interface that's for C I guess
right yes so you can you can generate
libraries that follow the platform
standard platform abia and then compile
rust to a dynamic library that can be
then linked from your Ruby Python
whatever program and that's a rather
common use case and I know a lot of
companies that kind of have a rust
library around for doing some heavy
lifting in the rails program the
standard example there being skylight
which has been around for three years as
a rescues or something because they have
picked rust even before it was stable
for saying okay we don't have enough c++
engineers here but we need some embedded
fast library in our product so what
we're going to do is we use a language
that's similar to C is easy embeddable
and embedded in our program on what they
do is they do metrics gathering in rails
applications for their clients which is
something we absolutely don't want to
ship something that SEC Falls because
that brings down your clients web
service absolutely don't and they were
seeing that a lot so there's been for a
long time basically people using rusts
and Python and all these languages said
well okay Ruby and Python if if it comes
slow we just replace it with a piece of
C but I've never seen that happening
because once once you ask people the
question okay but can you make sure that
this doesn't bring down our whole
machine here and like okay maybe we just
find all the machine and get along with
it and this is supported and often make
use case just to give a couple of others
we have we have piston which is a gaming
library which I can't cover behind
because I never used it shall be taught
by Chef is a new way of deploying
applique
Asians in onto infrastructures which
ships the libraries together with the
application and the whole tooling around
that is written in rust we see a lot of
tools in the DevOps world being written
with us nowadays timely data flow is
more of a research project that I just
want to drop the name off it's
implementing data flow through
infrastructure is with collecting of
data and doing computations of data as
it's a huge framework but there's a lot
of writing about it by the author
finally we have operating system
development in rusts so we're very happy
about that there's a growing community
of opera operating system implementers
there's one called a redux which already
boots into a graphical shell and all
these kind of things so you could use it
for something there's two very nice ones
intimate sauce and fills OS which are
meant for teaching operating systems so
they come with a lot of documentation on
why the implementations are like this
but also give interesting insights and
how to find safe abstractions for a lot
of these things for fils OS there's a
great blog post about how to implement
the memory management of the operating
system in a safe fashion and finally
Mozilla has started a project which is
called talk and it's an embedded
operating system currently just for
cortex processors but it's getting along
so let's talk a little bit about the
community so how many committees are
working on on rust right now do you have
any idea so it depends on who's the
committee so we have more than a
thousand different people contributing
to rust C and currently regular
committees are between five and ten
there's some people employed at Mozilla
this some people that work on server
that also commit to the compiler and all
these kind of things but it's definitely
a busy project but most of the people
actually work for Mozilla so it's sort
of Mozilla founder project
it's a bit more the other way around
there's a lot of people contributing but
definitely the people with large
contributions most of the time work for
Mozilla because being paid for working
on something just gives you a head start
but yes there's a there's a there's a
set of people working at Mozilla working
on the language design and working on
the compiler and also contributing to it
and also contributing to a lot of the
library X system around it and how's the
project organized so we have a set of
teams which you can find out rustling
but org slash teams that HTML and
there's a core team which cares for all
directional decisions around the
language they basically have the final
say on everything because someone in the
end needs to have it but rarely exercise
it they have to do all the work around
their RC process for example are you
with people about things plan new
features and what basic here implement
them there's a language design team and
the tooling team that's split off
working on these respective parts same
process though if there's a language
feature to be implemented or to be
proposed they have to go through an RFC
process there's a documentation team we
have also one person working full-time
on documentation of the language and we
generally get good marks on that
although there is still a lot to do like
implementing documentation for a
standard library in a proper fashion is
a year work so you said that you have we
rely on an RC process so how does that
work so you got to get up calm rustling
/ RFC's and there is a sample document
on how an RFC should look like and you
forked that and you start writing your
proposal for anything you'd like which
could be new methods for standard
library and for a standard library type
changes to certain behavior although
they need to be backwards compatible
we're pretty strict on backwards
compatibility
but before you said that you know a rust
actually removed quite a few features
that was before one hour so that there
was a reason why before one hour there
was a lot of feature cutting going on
for month the question basically was do
we want to commit on this and keep this
around four years a lot of stuff went
out of the language and a lot of stuff
was changed so nowadays that's not
possible in the general case anymore
from time to time there's the case where
for example someone finds a sound as
issue in the type system which needs to
be fixed which might lead to some
breakage but there's that's the point
where you really need to discuss and
whether that's something you need to
keep on how do you organize the
community obviously you're working in
particular on that part of rust so this
is the second set of teams one is the
community team which I am on and the
moderators team the moderators team is
there for well day to day moderation of
forums or subreddit and all these kind
of things we don't use mailing lists
anymore especially because they're bad
to be moderated we found that I need a
lot of new people don't really care
about my likeness that much anymore and
the community team itself works in a bit
of a very distributed fashion we meet
every week the meetings are open they're
in our time zone every Wednesday at 6:00
in the evening and there's another
meeting that sometimes happens that's
more for the Asian time zones so we try
to be approachable there it's open now I
see Channel you can always join in ask
questions and there is also a github
organization in which we plan new stuff
and the general angle of approach to the
community team is and that's been by far
the best we have an email you can write
us any question you want about rusts to
compile Oh what do I know if you don't
know if you don't know who to approach
and the project write a metal community
team and we bounce you off and that's
been a very simple and the workable
approach
how do you automate the the community
you said that this is actually is
something that is very specific about
the rest community it's always not to
say we automate the community but we
automate certain aspects of it for
example we have a thousand committers
and we I recently had a look at some of
the numbers usually a pull request in
the West Kampala sits for six days mean
and we merge a lot of them so there's a
lot of automation involved there and the
first thing is if you ever write a pull
request to any an issue on any of our
repositories that there's a bot which is
called hi-5 which just says hi you're
contributing he is a few things that we
have to say about that
and you're assigned the assign person
who this issue is someone and then hi-5
just picks a person and assigns that
issue to someone and instead of thinking
too much about that but who's
responsible for this thing I five just
signs anyone and that person's
responsibility is either to handle the
issue or to come up with a person that
should handle it which makes sure that
we have no unassigned issues anywhere
and everyone's cared for and that's
surprisingly simple and surprisingly
effective because a lot of problems that
open-source projects have are these
kinds of lingering issues that are in
no-man's land where no one knows who's
actually going to deal with them or
everyone thinks that someone else's job
and we just assigned the job of to
someone and we automate it bad and we
have a we have a merge part but it used
to be called Boers in one was see I
think it's still Boers there's an
reimplementation of that called homo and
what it does it tracks commits to master
or it it makes the commits to master so
what it does is on any pull requests you
can enter our plus as this is positively
reviewed or our - and if you get an R +
or what it does is it checks out the
pull request it checks out master merges
them runs all tests and one all pass
pass merges all this back into master
the advantage is that it holds queue of
these requests so he can review six or
seven pull requests and then the bot
will just start taking the first doing
that process committing to master and
after it's done continue on because the
problem there is that merging a pull
requests usually makes breaks all others
because then they're based off of a
different branch and all this busy work
is taken care of by that bot by saying
we have a standard continuous flow where
each of these is merged after another
and if anything happens we'll just come
back and say okay here I've got a
problem yeah and finally we have crater
and glacier crater is important for the
backwards guarantee so if we have a
feeling that there was a language change
that might lead to problems so for
example you have you change something of
a type system and you know that there's
an edge case which will then stop
working there's always the question is
anyone using that or how much breakage
would that lead to
so what crater does it pulls all crates
of our package repository that's which
is great say oh I guess we haven't
introduced the terms of a library in
rust that's called a crate and then it
compiles all of them and makes a report
of how many of these have failed
especially have there been any
regressions towards previous things like
we obviously have some libraries that
are broken so they don't compile anymore
so it's more like it tracks regressions
on an ecosystem wide scale so that we
have an idea on what how many problems
we have introduced
and finally there's a lot nice little
project called glacier which attracts
all compiler errors so if someone finds
a compiler error we write a small test
case in glacier that shows the compiler
crash and if it's fixed or not you said
that that you focus on backwards
compatibility so what happens if one of
those crates fails to compile because
you did to change to the language but
the language change be rejected because
that seems to be what backwards
compatibility would be about it depends
on the kind of change usually yes but as
I said for example in soundness for for
type system soundness fixes there's
always the question on okay there's one
crate that fails and 5,000 and don't but
this is an issue where for example you
could exec escape one of the safety
guarantees of the language this is
definitely debate to have especially at
the current state of the language if we
want to keep that around for next few
years so yes this standard would be
reject so how do I start you get to
community dot RS and that's a page we
just introduced last week and it holds a
lot of info on where to get started
where to find people to connect with
which are the forum's where does the
standard library documentation live all
these kind of things other than that
just go to rustling but work download
whatever we have there the compiler or
cargo and all these kind of things then
you just run install it run cargo in it
start coding if you don't want to do
that there's also an interactive
interpreter or an interactive compiler
sorry on Plato trust Lang gorg where you
can try out the language before it even
installing anything so a lot of meetups
provide hacking learns so here in Berlin
our standard meetup is we just meet and
code instead of someone giving you talk
I get the current state of the language
probably a talk is less and interesting
than a person giving you a short
introduction on how to approach your
problem with the language so we
try to have more people meeting
regularly just learning together also
our ISE channel gets great marks for
being friendly and we have the habit of
so it's frowned upon to tell newbies
that they should just read up before
they ask a question so there's a lot of
people around that usually have time for
answering your questions anything else
you want to add anything else I forgot
to ask you so in general of the
community team is always searching for
people that want to run a media or work
with us especially in in the southern
continents so um Australia Africa South
America we're very happy to have a
rather strong community in Brazil that's
global so we want to be a project that's
not just based around Europe and the US
and finally if you have some kind of
specific hobby I don't know some people
care about certain technologies and we'd
like to have an implementation in rust
that's we need a lot of libraries
currently so if you want to be the first
person to provide a certain library to
programming languages now it's the time
and finally if you are using rust and we
don't know of you I would be happy if
you could write to the community team
because what we also do out of quality
control reasons is we do interviews with
production users we'd be very interested
in interviewing you thanks a lot for the
interview and I wish you all the best
concerning for us and the rest community
thank you stay safe
[Music]
thanks for listening to se Radio an
educational program brought to you by I
Triple E software magazine for more
information about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website @ SC -
radioman to provide feedback you can
write comments on each episode on the
website or write a review on itunes
mention a message us on Twitter at se
radio or search for the software
engineering radio group on LinkedIn
Google+ or Facebook you can also email
us at team @ SC - radio net this and all
other episodes of SU radio is licensed
under the creative commons
two-point-five license thanks again for
your support
[Music]
[Applause]
you
[Music]